So let's see what does it take to have a
good cache or what are the properties of
a good cache. We want our system to have
a good average memory access time or AAT
and this is the access time to memory as
seen by the processor. The
AAT is equal to the cach's hit time. How
quickly can it return the data when we
do have a cash hit plus how often do we
have a miss times the miss penalty. We
want the AAT to be very low. The lower
the better. This means that we want the
hit time to be low which means we want a
small and fast cache because that will
contribute to having this be low. We
want a low miss rate, which means we
want our cash to be large and/or smart.
If it's a large cache, more stuff will
fit in it. So, we will miss less often.
Or if it's smart, it will know better
what to keep inside. So, again, we will
have fewer misses. The miss penalty for
simple caches is simply the main memory
access time. This is going to be very
large, usually tens or even hundreds of
processor cycles. So really when we're
designing caches, we're trying to
balance the hit time and the miss
rate. Small and fast versus large and
intelligent. And intelligent typically
means slightly
slower. So some caches can be extremely
small and fast, have very good hit time,
but sometimes that's at the expense of
having a larger miss rate. Some caches
will have a relatively large hit time
but extremely low miss rates so that we
can reduce the overall contribution of
main memory accesses that contribute a
lot each time we have them. Sometimes we
also talk about miss time which is the
overall time it takes to have a cache
miss. A miss time is simply the hit time
followed by the miss penalty because we
try to find what we have in the cache
but fail and then we still have to pay
the miss penalty. We can also think
about miss time is the memory access
time when we are missing. So miss rate
is one. So again it would be hit time
plus the miss penalty. So another way to
write the amat expression would be to
say that it is 1 minus miss rate times
the hit time. So this is how often do we
have the hits times the time for the hit
plus how often do we have the misses
times the miss time. Usually we want to
use this expression simply because the
miss time typically includes checking
whether what we have is in the cache
followed by whatever we need to do on a
miss. So somehow every time we will have
the time it takes to hit but sometimes
we will also pay the miss penalty.